<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A famous victory obtained, by Sir William Brewerton. Sir Thomas Fairfax. Sir William Fairfax. In a pitcht battle against the Lord Byron, (chief commander of the kings forces) at the raising of the siedge of Namptwitch. Together, with a list of all the commanders that were slain and taken in the said fight. Also, in what estate the towne of Namptwitch now is, and the miserable condition of the enemies forces in those parts. Printed according to order.</title>
            <author>Isack, J.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1644</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A87216</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing I1062</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E31_6</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R15513</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99859877</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99859877</idno>
            <idno type="VID">111978</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A87216)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 111978)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 6:E31[6])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A famous victory obtained, by Sir William Brewerton. Sir Thomas Fairfax. Sir William Fairfax. In a pitcht battle against the Lord Byron, (chief commander of the kings forces) at the raising of the siedge of Namptwitch. Together, with a list of all the commanders that were slain and taken in the said fight. Also, in what estate the towne of Namptwitch now is, and the miserable condition of the enemies forces in those parts. Printed according to order.</title>
                  <author>Isack, J.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Bernard Alsop,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Febr. the 2d. 1644.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed: I. Isack.</note>
                  <note>Attributed to J. Isack.  Cf. BLC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Brereton, William, --  Sir, 1604-1661.</term>
               <term>Fairfax, Thomas Fairfax, --  Baron, 1612-1671.</term>
               <term>Fairfax, William, --  Sir, 1609-1644.</term>
               <term>Byron, John Byron, --  Baron, 1598 or 9-1652.</term>
               <term>Nantwich (Cheshire) --  History --  Siege, 1644.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Campaigns --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:111978:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 61 -->
            <p>A FAMOUS VICTORY OBTAINED,</p>
            <list>
               <item>By Sir <hi>William Brewerton.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>By Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>By Sir <hi>William Fairfax.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>IN A pitcht Battle againſt the Lord BYRON, (Chief Commander of the Kings Forces) at the raiſing of the Sledge of <hi>Namptwitch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>TOGETHER, With a Liſt of all the Commanders that were ſlain and taken in the ſaid Fight.</p>
            <p>ALSO, In what eſtate the Towne of <hi>Namptwitch</hi> now is, and the miſerable condition of the Enemies Forces in theſe parts.</p>
            <p>Printed according to Order.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Bernard Alſop.</hi> Febr. <hi>the</hi> 2d. 1644.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:111978:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 62 -->
            <head>A FAMOVS VICTORY Obtained by Sir VVILLIAM BRERETON, Sir THOMAS FAIRFAX, and Sir WILLIAM FAIRFAX: Againſt the Lord BYRON: <hi>Chiefe Commander in the Kings Army.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>LL worthy Sir, I make no que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, but you have heard of the laſt defeat given to Sir <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholas Biron</hi> and his Serjant Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though Sir <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Brewerton</hi> hath beene much diſtreſſed in theſe parts,
<pb facs="tcp:111978:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 63 -->for want of ſupplyes, and although the Cowardlineſſe of the Mancheſter men; yet ſince they have gained their loſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, and ſtick to us with a great deale of valour, and at times done great executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on upon the enemy. The Lord <hi>Byron</hi> the Kings Generall, hath beene ſo terrible un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us, and ſheweth ſo little mercy on thoſe he overcommeth or taketh priſoners, that ſome of our forces were unwilling to venture on any deſigne, where <hi>Biron</hi> was; but ſince thanks be to God, our valiant Leaders, Sir <hi>William Brereton,</hi> Sir <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Fairfax,</hi> and Sir <hi>William Fairfax,</hi> and Colonell <hi>Mitton,</hi> have done ſo worthy good ſervices, that beleive from me, our Towne of Namptwich is for certaine ſet at liberty, the enemy quite routed; and diſperſed in ſeverall companies; that like amazed creatures they rove up and downe the country, and cannot make head of five hundred; which at the firſt beſi<gap reason="illegible: bleedthrough" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ging, was full five thouſand: our foot forces are greatly wearied, but exceeding good ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice
<pb facs="tcp:111978:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 63 -->
have they done, againſt the enemy: and as near as I can, I have ſet downe the truth of our late proceedings, with a Liſt of the number taken, and ſlaine. Wee are here very buſie for the preſent, and keepe a great Guard over the priſoners which wee have taken, and we beleive the Gentry ſhall be ſent to London, and the common Iriſh to be tryed by a Councell of Warre, the under-Marſhall and Keeper of our cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throates hath a beneficiall place thereof, of the Inhabitants, both men, women, and children, dayly reſort to the Goale, to ſee what manner of monſters they be. I beleive you will have this buſineſſe very ſuddenly, in regard of which, I will leave you, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping that you will pray for our further ſucceſſe, and reſt yours</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>I. ISACK.</signed>
               <dateline>From Crews-Houſe, <date>Ianuary the 29. 1644.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="list_of_prisoners">
            <pb facs="tcp:111978:4"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 64 -->
            <head>A Liſt of the Kings Commanders taken at the raiſing of the Siedge of <hi>Namptwich <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> in a pitcht Battle between Sir <hi>William Brewerton,</hi> Sir <hi>Thomas Fairfax,</hi> and Sir <hi>William Fairfax:</hi> Againſt the Lord <hi>Byron,</hi> chief Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander of the Kings Forces there.</head>
            <list>
               <item>SErgeant Major Generall <hi>Gibſon.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Michael Earmely.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Richard Fleetwood.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sir <hi>Francis Boteler.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Collonell <hi>Warren.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Collonell <hi>Moncke.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Collonell <hi>Gibs.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Major <hi>Hammond.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>
                  <gap reason="illegible: indecipherable" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 14, Captaines.</head>
               <item>1. Caſtillion.</item>
               <item>2. Wither.</item>
               <item>3. Leverſon.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:111978:4"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 64 -->
4. Caſe.</item>
               <item>5. Kiſe.</item>
               <item>6. Woodwofe.</item>
               <item>7. Pa<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e.</item>
               <item>8. Morgan.</item>
               <item>9. Lewis.</item>
               <item>10. Signum.</item>
               <item>11. Toothwood.</item>
               <item>12. Thomas.</item>
               <item>13. Lidcot.</item>
               <item>14. Billingſley.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>20. Lieutenants.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>1.</hi> Smith.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2.</hi> Bates.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3.</hi> Saintford, &amp;c.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>26. Enſignes.</head>
               <item>Browne.</item>
               <item>Brewerton, &amp;c.</item>
               <item>4. Canoneers.</item>
               <item>2. Cornets.</item>
               <item>2. Quartermaſters.</item>
               <item>1. Captatn Lieutenant of a Regiment.</item>
               <item>6. Peece of Ordnance.</item>
               <item>4. Trumpets.</item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:111978:5"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 65 -->
41. Sergeants.</item>
               <item>40. Drummes.</item>
               <item>61. Corporals.</item>
               <item>20. Carriages.</item>
               <item>120. Women with great Knives.</item>
               <item>200. Slain on the right Wing, beſides.</item>
               <item>700. Taken on the left Wing,</item>
               <item>21. Gentlemen of Companies.</item>
               <item>80. Fiery Bullets ſhot into the Town, but none did execution; but one, which lighted into a Stacke of Hay.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>Poſtcript.</head>
            <p>SIr my intentions were to have ſent you a more ample Relation, and to have certified you of each particular which happened both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and in the Fight, but the Meſſenger was in ſuch extraordinary haſte, I am forced to omit it till the next occaſion, intreating you to take this in good part.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Vale.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
